Guide to the Victoria Ortiz papers, 1942-1999 and undated, bulk 1960-1990 RL.00979
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Accession 2003-0204: Subject files, 1961-1984 and undated
  - Literature, Latin American Subseries, 1972-1974 and undated
    - Cruz, Artemio -- Notes (Box 11)
    - Cuba -- Guillén, Nicolas articles and bibliography (Box 11)
    - De Burgos, Julia -- Poetry (Box 11)
    - De Ibáñez, Sara (Box 11)
    - De Queiroz, Eça (Box 11)
    - Delbo, Charlotte -- Gaby's Dog, 1973 Aug. 11 (Box 11)
    - Depestre translation -- VO (Box 11)
    - Donoso, José -- Article (Box 11)
    - Films (Box 12)
    - Franco, Jean -- Notes (Box 12)
    - Fuentes, Carlos -- Articles (Box 12)
    - Galeano, Eduardo -- Articles (Box 12)
    - G. G. Márquez -- Blacaman the Good, Vendor of Miracles (Box 12)
    - Garcia Márquez -- Notes (Box 12)
    - Garro, Elena -- The Day When we Were Dogs (translation, VO) (Box 12)
    - Gods of Voodoo (Box 12)
    - Goytisolo -- Review of Count Julian (Box 12)
    - Guillén, Nicolas -- Articles (Box 12)
    - Hinostroza, Rodolfo (Box 12)
    - Huasipungo (The Villagers), Icaza (Box 12)
    - Huidobro, Vicente -- Poetry (Box 12)
    - Icaza, Jorge -- notes on Huasipungo (Box 12)
    - Lima, José Lezama (Box 12)
    - Llosa, Mario Vargas -- Articles (Box 12)
    - Marquéz, René -- The House of the Setting Suns (Box 12)
    - Marquez, Robert -- Introducción a Guillen (Box 12)
    - De Mello, Thiago -- What Counts is Life (Box 12)
    - Mendez, José Luis -- Literatura y Liberación Nacional en el Caribe (Box 12)
    - Mexican Literature -- Juan Rulfo and Octavio Paz (Box 12)
    - Notes -- Cuba and L.A. Territories (Box 12)
    - Notes -- Aztecs (Box 12)
    - Notes -- Franco, Jean (Box 12)
    - Notes -- Vallejo, Cesar -- El Tungsteno (Box 12)
    - Paper -- Brazil's Northeast Through the Eyes of Its Novelists, VO, 1973 Jan. (Box 12)
    - Paz, Octavio -- Reviews of works (Box 12)
    - Rulfo, Juan -- Notes (Box 12)
    - Surrealism and Negritude -- Notes (Box 12)
    - Valdez, Luis -- La Plebe (Box 12)
    - Voodoo and Santería -- Notes (Box 12)
    - Yanez, Augustin -- Notes (Box 12)
- Accession 2003-0204: Personal files
  Access Restrictions
  Closed until 2050.
  - Personal files (Box 13)
- Accession 2003-0066
  This container list describes only those materials that are currently open for research. Other materials are closed until 2050.
  Note: in many cases the donor has made notes on the folders themselves which give contextual information about the contents.
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - Ellos y Nosotros, book prepared by Ortiz's students and Elisabeth Irwin High School (Box 1)
    - CUNY Law School Catalogs (Box 1)
    - LEGSA papers (Box 1)
    - Articles about CUNY Law School (Box 1)
    - Interviews while in law school (Box 1)
    - Council on Interracial Books for Children issue about materials on Latin America (Box 1)
    - Post-hearing brief, prepared while Ortiz was intern at NYC Commission on Human Rights, AIDS Discrimination Unit (Box 1)
    - Gay and Lesbian materials (Box 1)
    - CUNY Law School Women's Journal (Box 1)
    - Materials from memorial service for Bobbye Ortiz (Box 1)
    - Guest-edited journal (Box 1)
    - Admission to Connecticut Bar (Box 1)
    - Reviews of Ortiz's book, The Land and People of Cuba (Box 1)
    - Materials on translation of Pedro Juan Soto's Spiks (Box 1)
    - Materials on Sojourner Truth book (Box 1)
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    - Copy of manuscript of Robert Chrisman's Children of Empire containing poem dedicated to Camilo (Ortiz's son) (Box 2)
    - Materials on translations of Norberto Fuentes' stories (Box 2)
    - Neruda translation (Box 2)
    - Concert program (Box 2)
    - Speaking engagements (Box 2)
    - Berkshire Forum, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - References to Sojourner Truth book (Box 2)
    - Cuban bookmarks (Box 2)
    - Council for Interracial Books for Children (Box 2)
    - Expression, literary magazing of Elisabeth Irwin High School (Box 2)
    - John Woolf exhibit materials (Box 2)
    - Elisabeth Irwin High School materials (Box 2)
    - Letter to the editor (Box 2)
    - Program from Greek Games at Barnard College, 1961 (Box 2)
    - The Feedback Agenda, CUNY Law School Yearbook, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Camilo Ortiz materials (Box 2)
    - Barnard Alumnae materials (Box 2)
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - Scrapbooks, ca. 1948-1960 (Box 3)
    - Book prepared by students in Latin American Literature in Translation class (Box 3)
    - Materials from visit to Cuba, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Chilean Women's Health Project (Box 3)
    - Pancho Mora catalogue (Box 3)
    - Cases from when Ortiz was litigation associate at Paul, Weiss, Rifking, Wharton and Garrison, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    - Cases from when Ortiz was litigation associate at Paul, Weiss, Rifking, Wharton and Garrison (Box 4)
    - Various songs (Box 4)
    - New York Law Journal Listing (Box 4)
    - Decisions by Civil Court Judge Margaret Taylor when Ortiz was her Court Attorney (Box 4)
    - Admission to various Bars (Box 4)
    - Letter from Siné (Box 4)
    - Thank you letters from students at Career Day (Box 4)
    - New York Council for the Humanities materials (Box 4)
  - Contents of Box 5: (Box 5)
    - Admission to various Bars (Box 5)
    - Materials on seamstresses union in Mexico City (Box 5)
    - Materials on Haywood Burns (Box 5)
    - Mini-grant report prepared at NY Council for the Humanities (Box 5)
    - Book review (Box 5)
    - Program funded by NY Council for the Humanities (Box 5)
    - Materials on Rosie the Riveter (Box 5)
    - Libros Lippincott en Español (Box 5)
    - Population Control article, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Contracts, publicity, reviews and correspondence regarding The Land and People of Cuba (Box 5)
    - TV appearance of Bobbye and Camilo Ortiz (Box 5)
    - Lippincott business (Box 5)
    - Reviews of Ortiz's translation of Che Guevara's Reminiscences of the Cuban Revolutionary War (Box 5)
    - Materials on the Rosenbergs (Box 5)
    - Correspondence regarding Ortiz's translation of Soto's Spiks (Box 5)
    - Convent of the Sacred Heart materials; Father Dennis Leder (Box 5)
    - Council on Interracial Books for Children, guest-edited issue (Box 5)
    - Article written as senior in high school, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
    - Greetings from the MIR, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Book jackets (Box 5)
    - UN Universal Declaration of Human Rights ceremony program translation (Box 5)
    - Sojourner Truth reviews, publicity (Box 5)
    - Poetry reading at Hampshire College (Box 5)
    - Speaking engagements (Box 5)
  - Contents of Box 6: (Box 6)
    - Audiocassettes from Bobbye Ortiz's memorial service (Box 6)
    - Audiocassettes of oral history interview of Bobbye Ortiz by Victoria Ortiz (Box 6)
    - Various publications (Box 6)
    - Volunteer ID tag (Box 6)
    - Gabriel Garcia Marquez portrait (Box 6)
    - Trip to Thailand, 1960 (Box 6)
    - Publicity for Sojourner Truth book (Box 6)
    - Speaking engagements (Box 6)
    - Unacknowledged translation of Neruda (Box 6)
    - Card from students at Sacred Heart, ca. 1981-1983 (Box 6)
    - Announcement of publication of Sojourner Truth book (Box 6)
    - Camilo's graduation from high school (Box 6)
    - CUNY Law School Women's Journal (Box 6)
    - Article co-authored with Jennifer Elrod for Women's Journal (Box 6)
    - Materials on racism and homophobia (Box 6)
    - Presentations at Berkshire Forum (Box 6)
    - Ortiz's graduation from Law School, 1988 (Box 6)
    - Minorities and women at Yale Law School (Box 6)
  - Contents of Box 7: (Box 7)
    - Articles about CUNY Law School (Box 7)
    - Materials on gay and lesbian issues from CUNY Law School (Box 7)
    - Study Guide from Women Make Movies (Box 7)
    - Paul, Weiss, Rifking, Wharton and Garrison, summer 1987 (Box 7)
    - Women and the Courts, NY Task Force Report (Box 7)
    - Booklet on slavery and the federal courts (Box 7)
    - Vietnam-era bumper stickers (Box 7)
    - Material from symposium on Halley's Comet (Box 7)
    - Clippings regarding Jennifer Elrod's clerkship (Box 7)
    - Materials on AIDS (Box 7)
    - Jury duty (Box 7)
    - Writings by friends (Box 7)
    - Vietman era bumper stickers (Box 7)
    - Greek Games at Barnard College, 1962 (Box 7)
    - Brochure from St. Christopher School (Box 7)
    - Book on Schomburg, xerox (Box 7)
    - Programs from drama events at St. Christopher School, ca. 1950s (Box 7)
    - Materials for proposed exhibit of Mexican art in England (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous unused postcards from Ortiz's collection (Box 7)
  - Contents of Box 8: (Box 8)
    - Artwork from St. Christopher's, 1950s (Box 8)
    - Yves Montand programs, one with autograph and dedication to Ortiz (Box 8)
    - Good luck wishes for Bar Exam (Box 8)
    - Clipping re: Wolf v. Barton (Box 8)
    - Correspondence re: Bobbye Ortiz's death (Box 8)
    - Cuban New Year's card (Box 8)
    - St. Christopher School alumni newsletter, 1999 (Box 8)
    - Box of political buttons (Box 8)
    - Spanish medal won by Bobbye Ortiz at NYU (Box 8)
    - Folded and gathered sheets of Victoria Ortiz's translation of Che Guevera (Box 8)
    - Copy of Ortiz's book The Land and People of Cuba, with inscription to Bobbye Ortiz (Box 8)
    - V.D. by Eric W. Johnson, copy with illustrations numbered and labels for Spanish edition (Box 8)
  - Contents of Box 9: (Box 9)
    - Two sets of folded and gathered sheets of Ortiz's book on Sojourner Truth (Box 9)
    - Clippings re: Legend of Pepito (Box 9)
    - New York and Connecticut Bar Exam documents (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous maps and tourist guides (Box 9)
  - Contents of Oversize folder 1: (Box Oversize 25)
    - John Hawkins prints (Box Oversize 25)
  - Boxes 10-25 (Box 10-25)
    Closed.
    - Personal papers, closed to use until 2050 (Box 10-25)
- Accession 2005-0024
  Boxes 1-13 are closed to use until 2050.
  - Boxes 1-13 are closed to use until 2050. (Box 1-13)